The following content is
provided under a Creative Commons license.
Your support will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high -quality educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to view additional
materials from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT
OpenCourseWare at ocw .mit .edu.
So we're really moving along
this review of the highlights of
linear algebra, and today it's matrices Q.
They get that name. They
have orthonormal columns.
So that's what one looks like. And then the key fact,
orthonormal columns translates directly into that
simple fact that you just keep remembering. Every time you see Q transpose
Q, you've got the identity matrix. Let's just see why. So Q transpose
would be,
I'll take those columns and make them into
rows.
And then
I multiply by Q with the columns.
And what do I get?
Well, hopefully I
get the identity matrix.
OK. Why?
Because Q, oh, yeah. The normal part tells me that the length
of each vector, that's the length squared Q transpose Q,
the length squared is 1.
So that gives me the 1 in the identity matrix all along
the diagonal. And then Q transpose times a different Q
is 0. That's the ortho part.
So that gives me the 0s.
So
that's a simple identity, but it translates
from a lot of words into a simple
expression.
Now, does
that mean that in the
other order,
Q Q transpose,
is that the identity?
So that's a
question to think about.
Is
Q Q transpose equal
the identity? Question.
Sometimes yes, sometimes no.
Easy to tell which.
The answer is yes.
Yes,
when Q is square.
The answer is yes. If
Q is a square matrix,
a square matrix, this
is saying that the square matrix Q
has that inverse on its left.
But for square matrices, a left inverse, Q
transpose,
is also a right inverse.
So for a square matrix, if you have an inverse that
works on one side, it will work on the other side.
So the answer is
yes in that case.
And then in that case,
that's the
case when we call Q is,
well, we really, I don't know what the right name
would be, but here's the name everybody uses,
an orthogonal matrix.
Only in this square case,
square.
Q is an orthogonal matrix.
Right. Do you want to
just see an example of how that works?
And it will not.
So if Q is rectangular,
let me do a rectangular Q and a square Q.
So I think there
must be a board up there somewhere.
Here.
OK.
Square.
All right.
Good
to see some orthogonal matrices,
because my message is that they are really
important in all kinds of applications.
Let's start 2 by 2. I can think of two different ways
to get an orthogonal matrix. That's a 2 by 2 matrix.
And one of them you
will know immediately.
Cos theta,
sine theta.
So that's a unit vector.
It's normalized.
Cos squared plus sine squared is 1.
And this guy has to be orthogonal to it. So
I'll make that minus sine theta and cos theta.
OK.
Those are both length 1.
They're orthogonal.
Then this is my Q.
And the inverse of
Q will be the transpose.
If I multiply,
the transpose would put the minus sign down here
and would produce the inverse matrix. And what does
that particular matrix
represent?
Geometrically, where
do we see that matrix?
It's a rotation. Thank you.
It's a rotation of the
whole plane by theta.
Yeah. So if I apply that
to 1, 0, for example,
I get the first column, which is cos theta,
sine theta.
And that's just
a rop. Let me draw a picture.
That
vector 1, 0
has got rotated up to.
So there's the 1, 0.
And there it got rotated through an angle theta. And
similarly, 0, 1 will get rotated through an angle theta
to there.
So the whole plane rotates.
Oh,
that makes me remember a highly important,
very important property of Q.
It doesn't change length.
The length of any vector is the same after you rotate it. The length
of any vector is the same after you multiply by Q. Can I just do that?
I claim any x, any vector x.
I want to
look at the length of Qx.
Same length as x.
Actually,
that's the reason in computations
that
orthogonal matrix are
so much loved,
because no overflow can
happen with orthogonal matrices.
Lengths don't change. I can multiply by any number
of orthogonal matrices, and the lengths don't change.
Can we just see why that's true?
How would you show?
So what do we have to go on?
What
we have to go on is Q transpose Q equal i.
Whatever we're going to prove, it's got to
come out of that, because that's all we know.
So how do I
use that to get that one?
Well, we haven't said a whole lot about lengths, but you'll see it
all now. It'll be easier to prove that the squares are the same.
So what's the matrix expression for the length
squared? What's the right -hand side of that equation?
X transpose x,
right?
X transpose x gives me
the sum of the squares.
Pythagoras says that's the length squared.
So that right -hand side is x transpose x.
What's the left side?
It's the length squared of Qx.
So it must be the same as Qx transpose Qx.
And the claim is
that that equation holds.
And do you see it?
Where is it? So
any property from
Q has to just come out directly from that.
Where is it here?
Do I just push away a little bit
at that left -hand side and see it?
Qx transpose is the
same as x transpose Q transpose.
And Qx is Qx.
And now I'm seeing, well, you might say, wait
a minute. The parentheses were there and there.
But I say the most important law for matrix multiplication is you
can move parentheses or throw them away. Let's throw them away.
So in here, I'm seeing Q transpose Q, which
is the identity.
So it's true.
Yeah.
So that means that you never underflow
or overflow when you're multiplying by Q.
Every numerical algorithm is written to you
to use orthogonal matrices wherever it can.
OK.
And here's the first example.
I think it may be good for me to think of other
examples, or for us to think of other examples
of orthogonal matrices.
So I'm using that
word orthogonal matrix.
We should really
be saying orthonormal.
And
I'm really thinking mostly of square ones.
So in
the
square case, when Q transpose is Q inverse.
Of course,
that fact makes it easy to solve all equations that have Q as a coefficient
matrix, because you want the inverse and you just use the transpose. OK.
Let's just take
some minutes to think of examples of Qs. If they're
so important, there have to be interesting examples.
And that was a first one. Now, there's one
more 2 by 2 example that you should know.
Do you know what that would be?
So another,
this will be example 2.
And it's also going to be only 2
by 2.
And real.
And what
possibility have I got left here?
I'll use the same first column,
cos theta
sine theta, because that's more or less any
unit vector
in two dimensions. This has got that form.
So
what do you propose for the second column?
Yes?
So theta more or less
times theta.
GILBERT STRANGER GILBERT STRANGER Yeah. Put
the minus sign down here.
So you think, does that make any
difference?
So sine theta and
minus cos theta.
I don't
know if you've ever looked at that matrix.
We're trying to collect together a few matrices that are worth knowing,
are worth looking at. OK. Now, what's happened here? You may say that was a
trivial change,
which it kind of was.
But it's a different matrix now.
That's not a rotation.
And yeah, somehow, now
it's symmetric.
And yeah,
it's eigenvectors. Must
be something or other. We'll get to those.
But what does that
matrix do? I don't know. I don't
know if you've seen it. If you haven't,
it doesn't jump out. But it's an important
case.
This is a reflection matrix.
Notice that it's
determined it is minus 1.
You have minus cos squared theta minus sine squared theta. It's determined
it is minus 1. There's some eigenvalue coming up that's got a minus. Yeah.
OK. So what do I mean by
a reflection matrix? Let me draw a plane.
And I think,
so 1, 0.
Let's follow it again.
1, 0, where does that go? That gives me the
first column. So as before,
it goes to cos theta,
sine theta.
At angle theta.
And
halfway between was the theta over 2 line.
That's OK.
Now, what about the other guy, 0,
1?
Here's 0, 1.
OK. I multiply that.
Can I put the 0, 1
up here so your i does the multiplication?
Where is the result of 0, 1?
What's the output from q applied
to 0,
1?
Sine theta minus cos theta, right? It's the
second column.
And so where is that?
Well, it's perpendicular to that
guy. That's why I know,
right? That was the point,
that the two columns are perpendicular.
So it must go
down this way, right?
Sine theta cos theta.
And it doesn't change length.
All these facts that we
just learned
are key.
So there's 0, 1. And it goes
to this guy,
which
is
whatever that second column is, sine theta
minus cos theta.
And if you check that,
actually,
gosh, this is like plane geometry.
I believe,
it never occurred to me
before, but I believe it,
that this angle going down
to there, that that goes straight through,
and that the halfway one is that
line.
Yeah, I think that picture
has got it. And I think it's in the notes.
So that's a reflection matrix.
Well, that's a 2
by 2 reflection matrix.
See
some other matrices like
this one, but larger.
They're named after a
guy named Householder.
So these are
Householder reflections.
What am I doing here?
I'm collecting together some orthogonal
matrices that are useful and important.
And Householder found a whole bunch of them. And his
algorithm is a much used part of numerical linear algebra.
So he
started with a unit vector.
Start with
a unit vector
u transpose u equal 1.
So the length of
the vector is 1.
And then he
created, let's name it after him,
h. He created this matrix.
The identity
minus 2 u u transpose.
And I
believe that that's a really useful matrix.
So it's just like,
I think this review is
like going beyond 1806 into what ones
are really
worth knowing individually.
OK, could we just check what are the properties of Householder's
reflection of that i minus 2? You recognize here a column times a row.
So that's a matrix.
And what could
you tell me about that
matrix u u transpose?
It's, yeah,
what?
Or what can we say about h?
So I guess I'm believing that h is an orthogonal
matrix. Otherwise, it wouldn't be here today.
So I believe that.
And not only is it orthogonal, it is also,
have a look at it. Symmetric.
It's
also symmetric. The identity is symmetric.
u u transpose is symmetric. So this is
a family of symmetric orthogonal matrices.
And that was one of them.
That's a
symmetric orthogonal matrix.
And these matrices are really
great to have. You just,
like in using linear algebra,
it's, you just get a collection of useful matrices that
you can call on. And these are definitely one family.
Well, it's obviously symmetric.
Shall we check that it's orthogonal?
So to check that it's
orthogonal, I just, so I'm going to check
that h transpose h is
the identity.
Can I just check that?
Well, h transpose is the same as h, because it was symmetric.
So I'm going to square this guy. This is really h times h.
I'm squaring it.
And what do I get if I square?
So I get,
I
hope I get the identity, but let's see it.
What do I
get when I square? This?
Get a little,
multiply it out.
So i times i is i.
And then I get some number of u u transposes.
How many do I get for the, from that?
So I'm squaring this thing, because
h transpose h is the same as h times h.
So I'm squaring it. So how many, what do I
put here?
4.
And now I've got this guy squared with a
plus. So that's 4 u u transpose u u transpose.
Yeah, I'm totally realizing I've practiced for a
lifetime doing these dinky little calculations.
But
they are dinky.
And you'll get the hang of it quickly. Now,
what am I hoping out of that bottom line?
That it is?
i.
We're hoping to get i.
Do we get i? Yes.
Who sees how to get i
out of that thing?
u transpose u. GILBERT
STRANGSKI. Yeah.
u transpose
u in here is a number.
That was u, that was column times row
times column times row. And I look at the,
in the middle here is row times column. And
that's the number 1, right? Because it's there.
So that's 1. And then I have minus 4 of that, plus
4 of that. They cancel each other. And I get i.
So those are good matrices.
We'll use them.
We'll use them. Actually, they're better than Gram
-Schmidt. So we'll use them in making things orthogonal.
So what other
orthogonal matrices?
We'll create some.
You know,
creating good
orthogonal matrices is,
you know, it
pays off. Let's think.
So there's a family named after this French
guy
who lived
to 100. He was a real old timer.
Well,
MIT had a faculty member in math
when
I came, Professor Stroik, who lived to 106.
And I heard him give a lecture at Brown University at age 100.
And it was like perfect. You could not have done it better.
So he's my inspiration.
I keep going.
I only have like
n more years to get there.
And n is, well,
it's too many anyway.
OK. Adam Arn.
All right. Adam Arn. So
Adam Arn, he
stated, well,
that's the simplest,
the smallest.
Now,
the next guy is
going to be 4 by 4. I'm going to put that.
So where I see a 1,
I'm going to put Adam Arn. 1, 1,
1 minus 1, 1, 1, 1 minus 1.
And then when I see a
minus, I'm going to put it in with a minus.
You saw that picture?
It
was a picture of H2, H2, H2, and minus H2.
That's what I've got there.
And I believe those
columns are orthogonal.
Right?
Now, what could I do? Well, it's not quite
an orthogonal matrix. What do I have to do?
To make it, this isn't quite an orthogonal matrix
either. What do I do to make that an orthogonal matrix?
Divide by
square root of 2.
I need unit vectors there.
And here, those lengths are 1 squared, 1 squared, 4.
Square root of 4 is 2. So I better divide by the 2 there.
And now here, I'm going to, here I'm up to,
yeah. So that was.
That one.
Tell me the next one up.
What's that going to be? 8 by 8?
So this is H4 here.
Oops, 4.
So tell me what I should
do for 8 by 8. You'll think this is simple.
But that's a good
thing to say about it.
There,
in coding theory, all sorts of places, you
want matrices of 1's and minus 1's.
OK. What's H8?
I'm going to build it out of H4.
So
what am I going to, what's it going to be?
I'm going to put an H4
there. What am I going to put here?
Another H4.
And up here?
Another H4. And finally here?
Minus H4.
And I think I've
got an orthogonal matrix.
Columns again. Right?
Because
the columns within these
dot products with themselves
give 0 and 0.
The dot products from these columns and these columns obviously have the
minus. And the dot products in here are 0 from that and 0 from that. Yeah.
It works.
It doesn't come directly from our little
pattern, which is doubling size every time.
But you could still hope.
And it works.
There
is a, I don't know what it is, but
there's a matrix
of 1's and minus 1's orthogonal,
12 orthogonal columns.
So the answer is yes.
OK.
So we make an 18 .065
conjecture.
Every matrix, every matrix size
Well, not every matrix
size, because 3 by 3 is not going to work.
1 by 1 is not
going to work either.
But H12 works. H8, H16.
What's our conjecture?
We won't be the first to conjecture it. That there is a
1's and minus 1's orthogonal matrix with orthogonal columns
of every size n.
So always,
so I'll start the conjecture.
Always possible
if n,
which is
the size of the matrix, let's say,
what would you guess?
Just take a shot. You won't be asked
for a proof, because nobody has the proof.
Even?
Well, you could hope for even.
You could look for, try 6, I guess, would be the
first guy. There and I don't think it's possible.
I think 6 is not possible.
So every even size is,
I think, not going to work.
But it's a natural idea to try.
What's the next thought?
Every multiple of 4. If n
over 4 is a whole number.
So but nobody has a way, a systematic way,
to create these things.
So like some of them, at this point, we're
down to doing it one at a time.
And we're up to 668.
But we haven't got that one yet.
Isn't that crazy? So all this is
coming from Wikipedia,
my source.
My
source of all that's good in mathematics is
there on Wikipedia.
Anyway, this is the conjecture.
Conjecture means you don't have
any damn idea of whether it's true or not.
Is that divisible by 4?
Yeah, I guess it would be.
600 certainly is, and
68 certainly is. Yeah.
OK. So I think
that's the first one.
So anybody, if you find one of size 668, just skip the whole thing.
Homework and tell us about that one. But I don't think I'll assign that.
Yeah. I guess, well,
yeah, I must have
searched for it online.
But yeah.
Anyway,
so
those are the atom -r matrices.
Now, where else do I remember
orthogonal matrices coming from?
Well.
Yeah, really,
the biggest source of,
so when I'm
looking for orthogonal matrices,
I'm
looking for a basis of orthogonal vectors.
And where in
math am I going to find
vectors that come
out to be orthogonal?
We haven't seen that. It's the next section
of the notes. But maybe you're remembering.
Where will
we sort of like
automatically show up
with orthogonal vectors?
They could be
the eigenvectors of a?
Symmetric.
And that's where
the most
important ones come from.
Oh, I could tell you about wavelets, though. Wavelets are more like this
picture. They're ones and minus ones. Or the simplest wavelets are ones and
minus ones. Before I go on
to the eigenvector business, can I mention
the wavelets matrices?
Yeah, these
are really important,
simple and
important constructions.
So wavelets,
let me, yeah,
let me draw a picture of,
so
I'm going to
come up with four. I'll do the 4 by 4 case.
And these are the
orthogonal guys.
And then the next one is up.
And down.
And 0.
And the last one is 0. And up.
And down.
So that's four things. But let me show you
the matrix. So I'll call it w for wavelets.
So that guy I'm thinking
of as 1, 1, 1, 1.
This guy
I'm thinking of as 1, 1, minus 1, minus 1.
It's
looking sort of Atomard way.
But there's a difference here. This guy is
1, minus 1, 0, 0. So the wavelets rescale.
That's the difference
between Atomard and wavelets.
Wavelets
are scaling,
self -scaling. And
what's the last guy here?
What's
the fourth column from that fourth wavelet?
0,
1,
minus 1.
Yeah.
So Haar came up with that.
This is the Haar wavelet,
which was many years before the word
wavelets was invented.
He came up
with this construction.
The
Haar matrix, the Haar functions.
So they're
very simple functions.
But
that makes them usable,
the fact that they're so simple.
Now,
I don't know if you want to
see the pattern in 8 by 8. But let me start the
8 by 8. So you'll know what wavelets are about.
You'll know
what these Haar wavelets are about anyway.
They're the ones that were kind of easy to
visualize.
So if that's w4,
let's just take a minute.
It won't take long for w8.
OK. So the first
column is going to be 8,
1. And
what's the next column
going to be?
4, 1s and 4, minus 1s, like so.
So 4, 1s
and 4, minus 1s.
OK. And now the next column.
2, 1s. Two 1s,
2, minus 1s, and 0s.
Right?
1, 1, minus 1, minus 1, and 0s.
And the fourth will be 0s
and 2, 1s and 2, minus 1s.
We've got half a matrix now.
Now, if we
just tell me the fifth,
what do you think?
What do I put in the fifth one?
So again,
it's going to
squeeze down and rescale.
And what's the fifth column up here that's
going to be 1s and minus 1s and 0s now?
So it's not Adamard.
It's Haar.
And what shall I put? 1,
1. 1, 1.
How's it? Shall I start with 1, 1?
1 minus 1. Oh, 1 minus 1. Yeah.
And then all 0s?
Oh, yeah. Thanks. Perfect.
1, minus 1, and then all 0s. And then the next three columns will have
the 1, minus 1 here, and the 1, minus 1 here, and the 1, minus 1 here. And
otherwise, all 0s. Yeah.
So you see the pattern.
It's scaling at every step.
And so that
matrix has the advantage
of being quite sparse.
Sort
of this, in my mind, is a 4, 1s.
That's
involved with taking the average.
Then
this guy is like
taking the differences,
differences
between those and those.
And then this is like
taking the difference
at a smaller scale,
and
that also at a smaller scale. So that's what
we keep doing. Yeah. Yeah. So that's wavelets.
It looks so simple, right?
But just a one -minute history of wavelets.
I invented this
in like 1910. I mean,
how long?
Forever.
But then you
wanted wavelets that were a little better,
and not
just 1s and minus 1s and 0s. And that took
a lot of thinking. A lot of people
were searching for it. And Ingrid Dovishy,
so I'll just put her name,
became famous for finding them.
So in about 1988,
she
found a whole lot of families of wavelets.
And when I say wavelets, she found a whole
lot of orthogonal matrices
that had good properties.
Yeah. So that's the wavelet picture.
OK.
Now, to close today
and to connect with
the
next lecture on eigenvalues, eigenvectors,
positive definite
matrices, we're really
getting to the
heart of things here.
Let me
follow through on that idea.
So the eigenvectors
of a symmetric matrix,
but also of
an orthogonal matrix,
are orthogonal.
And that is really where people,
where you can invent,
because you don't have to work hard.
You just find a symmetric matrix.
Its
eigenvectors are automatically orthogonal.
Great for use, but some
of them are
really important.
And maybe the most important of all is the
Fourier.
So you probably have seen Fourier series, sines
and cosines. Those guys are orthogonal functions.
But the discrete
Fourier series is what everybody computes.
And those
are orthogonal vectors.
So the orthogonal vectors
go into the
discrete Fourier transform.
And then they're done at high speed by the
fast Fourier transform.
Those are eigenvectors of Q,
eigenvectors of the right Q.
So let me just invent
the right, tell you the right Q,
whose eigenvectors.
So here we go.
Eigenvectors
of Q.
Let me, you will just
be amazed by how simple this matrix is.
It's just
that matrix.
It's called
a permutation matrix.
It just puts the,
those are the
Fourier, four Fourier
discrete.
Discrete, let me put the
word discrete up here,
transform.
So I really meant
to put discrete Fourier transform.
Yeah.
The eigenvectors of that matrix,
first of all, they are
orthogonal.
And then
second and more important,
they're tremendously useful.
They're the heart
of signal processing.
In signal processing,
they just take the discrete Fourier transform of a vector before they
even look at it. I mean, that's the way to see it, is split it into its
frequencies.
And that's what the eigenvectors of this will do. So
we're going to see the discrete Fourier transform.
But my point here
is to know that they're orthogonal
just comes out of this fact that
the eigenvectors are orthogonal for
any Q. And
that is certainly a Q.
Everybody
can see that those
columns are orthogonal.
The columns of
a perm, that's a permutation matrix, right?
You've taken the columns of the identity, which are totally
orthogonal. And you just put them in a different order.
So a permutation matrix is a reordering of
the identity matrix.
It's got to be a Q.
And therefore,
its eigenvectors
are orthogonal. And they're just
the winners.
I mean, the matrix of,
the Fourier matrix with those
four eigenvectors in it, I'll show you now.
OK. So this is really,
we're finishing.
Today, by
leading into Wednesday,
eigenvectors and eigenvalues.
And we happen to be
doing eigenvectors and eigenvalues of a Q,
not
today of an S.
Most of the time, it's a symmetric matrix whose
eigenvectors we take. But here, that happens to be a Q.
Can I show you the eigenvectors?
The four eigenvectors of that.
The complex number i is
going to come in. You have
to let it in here.
Yeah, sorry.
If S is a real symmetric
matrix, its eigenvectors are real.
But if Q is a orthogonal matrix, its eigenvectors, even
though you couldn't ask for a more real matrix than that.
But its eigenvectors are
at least, yeah, the good
way are complex numbers. So can I show you
the eigenvectors of?
OK.
So again, overall, the
point today is to see orthogonal matrices.
So I'll just
repeat now while I can.
Reflections here.
Reflections.
Wavelets.
The householder idea of reflections of large
matrices that have this form, i minus 2 uu transpose,
are orthogonal. And now we're going to see
the big guys,
the eigenvectors of Q.
Right.
Yes?
Do you want to rescale the column? Oh, yeah. We don't have
orthonormal. That's right. We don't have orthonormal. I better
divide by square root of 8.
Right. Or
is it a different form?
Oh, yes. Oh, you're right.
Sorry. I thought
I'd get away with that, but I didn't.
Yeah.
These guys are square roots of 8. So are these. But these guys are square
roots of 4. And these guys are square roots of 2. Thank you. Absolutely
right.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
OK. So
what are the eigenvectors of a permutation?
This is going to be nice to see.
And I'll use the
matrix F for the eigenvector matrix.
So I'm going to ask you for
the eigenvector matrix of that Q up there.
And F is for Fourier.
And it'd be the 4 by 4 Fourier
matrix. OK. What are the eigenvectors of Q?
OK.
So Q is a permutation.
So I'm going to ask
you for one eigenvector
of every permutation matrix.
What vector can you tell me that? Actually, the eigenvalue will be 1.
What vector can you tell me where if I permute it, I don't change it?
1, 1, 1, 1.
It's like
it's everywhere here. 1, 1, 1, 1.
So that's the zero frequency
Fourier vector, the constant vector,
all ones.
Everybody sees
that if I multiply by Q, it doesn't change.
OK. Now, the next one,
I'll show you the 4 now.
The next one will be 1i,
i squared and i cubed.
Of course, i squared,
I don't know how many course
6j people are in this audience. But this is a math building. We
paid for it. It's 2 ,190. And it's i in this room. Yeah. So yeah.
Anyway,
i is the first letter in what?
Imaginary. Imaginary. Thank you. The first
letter in imaginary. You can't say jimaginary.
So that's it. OK.
And then the next
one is 1i squared i fourth i sixth.
And the next
one is 1i cubed i sixth
and i ninth.
Isn't that just beautiful?
And you could
show that every
one of those four columns, if you multiply
them by Q, you would get the eigenvalues.
And
you would see
that it's an eigenvector.
And this is just sort of like a discrete
Fourier stuff. And instead of e to the i,
e to the ix, e to the 2ix, e to the
3ix, and so on, we just have vectors.
So those are
the four eigenvectors.
I can implement the Well,
I should really say
zeroth -column and first -column if
I'm talking frequencies.
Do you see that that's orthogonal to that? Well, y is 1 plus i
plus i squared plus i cubed equals 0. That's the dot product.
This is column 1 dot column 2.
Yeah,
you're right.
This happens to come out 0. Is that right?
That'll come
out 0.
But somebody mentioned
that this isn't right.
I mean, it's true
that that came out 0. But
when I have imaginary
numbers anywhere around,
this isn't the correct dot product to test
orthogonal.
If I have imaginary complex vectors,
if I have complex numbers, complex vectors,
I should test column 1
conjugate dotted with column 2,
column i conjugate. Well,
let me take
column 1.
See, which one
shall I take? Maybe that guy and that guy.
Many of them you luck out here.
But really, I should be
taking the conjugate. So these 1s. But the thing
is the complex conjugate of 1 is 1. So that was OK.
But in general, if
I wanted to take column
dotted with column,
I
don't know,
maybe 4 would be a little dodgy.
Yeah, look what happens.
Take that column
and that column.
Take their dot product.
Do it the wrong way.
So what's the wrong way?
Forget about the complex conjugate and just do it
the usual way. So 1 times 1 is 1. i times i cubed is?
1.
i squared times i 6 is?
1. I'm getting all 1s.
I'm not getting orthogonality there. And that's because I forgot that I
should take the complex conjugate. Well, of these guys, 1. I should take
minus i,
minus i square, minus i. Well, that's real.
So it's OK.
Minus there.
So minus i squared is
still minus 1.
So now if I
do it, it comes out 0.
So let me repeat again.
Let me just make this statement.
If Q transpose Q
is i, and Qx is lambda x,
and Qy is a
different eigenvalue y,
OK.
So I'm setting up the main fact that in the last minute, I'm
just going to write down. So I have an orthogonal matrix.
I
have an eigenvector with eigenvalue lambda.
I have another
eigenvector with a different eigenvalue mu.
Then the
claim is that, what is the claim?
About the eigenvectors.
So here it has one eigen. This has an
eigenvalue. This has a different eigenvalue.
I need them to be different to really know
that
the x's and the y's can't be the
same. So what is it that I want to show?
Conjugated x is orthogonal. GILBERT STRANG.
GILBERT STRANG. Yes. That x,
and I have
to remember to do that, x transpose y is 0.
That's orthogonality.
That's orthogonality for complex vectors. I have to remember
to change every i to a minus i in one of the vectors.
And I can prove that fact by
playing with starting from here. I can get
to that.
OK. We've done a lot today. A lot of stuff
about orthogonal matrices.
Important ones.
Sources of important ones.
Eigenvectors.
And so
it'll be eigenvectors on Wednesday.